Guide to the United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 Photographs, Part I: Negatives PHOTOS.023
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 Photographs- Part I: Negatives and Interpositives
Bulk, 1940-1959
1938-1969
PHOTOS.023
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
32.0 linear feet (32 boxes)
District Council 65, United Automobile Workers (UAW) was organized in 1933 by a group of Jewish workers employed in dry goods warehouses on New York's Lower East Side. In 1935 it became a local of the Wholesale Dry Goods Employees Union; subsequently, it affiliated with the Distributive Trades Council of New York and the Retail Wholesale and Department Store Union (RWDSU); it affiliated with the UAW in 1979. The union went out of existence in 1994, when bankruptcy forced it to close. Between 1937 and 1942, District 65 was at the center of a group of New York City left-wing locals organizing large numbers of warehouse and retail workers; it later expanded its organizing to include white-collar workers in publishing and universities. Politically active in areas beyond its own immediate concerns, District 65 was an early participant in the civil rights movement, as well as one of the first labor unions to publicly oppose the Vietnam War. It also took a progressive stance within its own organization, with rank and file members playing an active role in their union. The collection consists of nearly 30,000 black and white negatives spanning the late 1930s through the early 1960s, with the bulk from the 1940s and 1950s, shot by members of District 65's own Camera Club, which functioned as staff photographers for the union's newspaper. The images document the everyday organizational life of District 65, its leaders and its diverse membership (including men and women of Jewish, African-American, Irish and Hispanic descent), while at the same time providing especially strong documentation generally for left and liberal causes of the 1940s-1960s, including civil rights, rank and file participation in union activities, working class leisure and recreational activities. Also included are images of prominent left-wing and liberal politicians, entertainers, and celebrities.
International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America. District 65.
General note
Open for research without restrictions.
NOTE: 5,200 of the images from this Collection, with searchable captions and dates, may be viewed online--both on-site and remotely--via the ARTstor website at http://library.artstor.org/library/welcome.html by researchers who are affiliated with New York University. Researchers not affiliated with New York University may view these images online only while visiting the Tamiment Library.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Automobile, Aircraft, and Vehicle Workers of America, District 65 Records (WAG 006)
United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 Oral History Collection (OH 019)
United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 016)
Roger Keeran Photographs (PHOTOS 187)
Ed Roth Photographs Collection (PHOTOS 160)
Provenance
Donated by the International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America between 1979-1981.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
NOTE: 5,200 of the images from this Collection, with searchable captions and dates, may be viewed online--both on-site and remotely--via the ARTstor website at http://library.artstor.org/library/welcome.html by researchers who are affiliated with New York University. Researchers not affiliated with New York University may view these images online only while visiting the Tamiment Library.
Scope and Contents note
The Collection consists of nearly 30,000 black and white negatives spanning the late 1930s through the early 1960s, with the bulk from the 1940s and 1950s. Besides documenting the life and times of the union itself, these images provide especially strong documentation for left and liberal causes of the 1940s-1960s, including civil rights, rank and file participation in union activities, and working class leisure and recreational activities. Also included are images of prominent left-wing and liberal politicians, entertainers, and celebrities, such as Eleanor Roosevelt, Martin Luther King, Paul Robeson, Harry Belafonte, Vito Marcantonio, and Henry Wallace. What particularly distinguishes these photographs from most collections of labor union images—which are largely limited to formal shots of the leadership and its activities—is that the Collection documents the everyday organizational life of District 65 and that of its diverse membership(including men and women of Jewish, African-American, Irish and Hispanic descent), as well as its leaders. Still more unusual, and probably unique among photographs shot for labor unions, the images were shot by District 65's own Camera Club, which functioned as staff photographers for the union's biweekly newspaper. Because these volunteer photographers were themselves members of District 65, shooting from the inside of the organization, they were able to capture more relaxed, intimate views of fellow members than the images shot by the commercial contract photographers usually engaged by other unions.
In the process of recording the organizational occupational, recreational, and political activities, and (occasionally) the home lives of its members and leaders, District 65’s photographers also captured a wealth of valuable historical and social information. Warehouses, offices, factories; the storefronts, facades, and interiors of dozens of department stores (the union’s members worked in dozens of now-vanished department stores that were then ubiquitous in cities large and small throughout of the U.S.), marquees and interiors of hotels, auditoria, nightclubs, and other public spaces; young working people at parties and dances and engaged in amateur team sports, retired workers, workers’ homes and workplaces, streetscapes of New York City, and unguarded social interactions of working people are only some of the examples of the types of visual data that can be discerned from these images. In many cases the “unintentional” documentation that is contained in these images may as valuable as the documentation they hold of the events they were meant to record.
A great strength of the Collection is that caption information and/or dates are available for almost all of its images. Moreover, at least one of the photographs shot of each event or person was usually published in the union’s newspaper, which means that in nearly every instance it is possible to learn more (sometimes much more) about an image(s) of a given event or person, as well as its wider context, than what is available in its caption alone, simply by consulting the story in which it was published.
The basic unit of the Collection is the "shoot"--a group of negatives or a single negative shot by one or more photographers of one event that usually, but not always, takes place on the same day. Series II and III are comprised of 5,200 images made into interpositives and duplicate negatives made from original negatives selected from the Collection for archival preservation. These are arranged in negative number order.
Series I, Negatives, comprises all the original negatives and represents a complete list of the shoots in the collection, arranged into ten subject subseries. Within each subseries these shoots are grouped into by event, organization, or person into individual entries, and the entries are arranged alphabetically by the first word of the title(s) assigned to them. Each entry includes a negative number (or series of negative numbers), a title comprised of a shoot description(s) drawn the original caption information, and a date(s), if known. The dates given are not necessarily the actual dates an event took place; they represent the day that a photographer was assigned to cover an event, although the two dates often coincided and photography assignments were rarely given out more than one or two days before an event was photographed. When its subject content falls into more than one category the same individual negative or shoot may appear under more than one subject subseries. The location of specific negatives is indicated in the location list directly above the container list in this finding aid.
SUBSERIES I:A - DEMONSTRATIONS, RALLIES, PARADES, STRIKES - 1938-1969.
These images record both public manifestations of the union’s activities on its own behalf (including preparations for strikes, strike picket lines, organizing, and leafleting) and its participation in larger actions or campaigns organized by other labor unions or organizations, such as annual May Day and Labor Day parades, civil rights and anti-war marches.
SUBSERIES I:B - INDIVIDUALS - 1939-1969.
Portraits of individuals and group portraits: Group portraits include groups of individuals (mostly from within the union) such as locals, committees, union sports teams, negotiating committees, strikers, convention attendees, while individual portraits, which form the bulk of this subseries, are mostly of rank and file District 65 members, but also include District 65 officers, as well as individuals from outside of the union, including New York City and state, national, and international labor union leaders, politicians, and celebrities who supported or solicited support from the union. The latter group includes New York City mayors O’Dwyer and Wagner, Senators Robert F. Kennedy; Jacob Javits, and Wayne Morse; Eleanor Roosevelt, the NAACP’s Walter White, A. Philip Randolph, and Martin Luther King, Jr. Images that were shot for the newspaper’s regular “Portrait” and “Capsule Biography” features have those designations included in their captions. (“Portraits” features showed members’ photographs alone; in “capsule biographies” the images were accompanied by a brief biographical sketch of the member photographed.) Also noted in captions are those photographs that were shot for the “Inquiring Photographer” feature, in which reporters solicited members’ opinions on various questions (usually on then-current union, political, or social questions).
SUBSERIES I:C - LOCALS OUTSIDE OF NEW YORK CITY - 1943-1968.
While the greatest concentration of District 65’s members by far were employed in New York City, a significant number also worked in the wider metropolitan area that included of New Jersey, Connecticut, and in suburban areas of New York state. Locals were also organized in states outside of the metropolitan area. Best represented among these out- of-town locals are those from the South, including Alabama, Arkansas, District of Columbia, Florida, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, Texas, and Virginia. Also documented photographically are locals from the mid-Atlantic and Midwest states of Pennsylvania, Illinois, Iowa, Missouri, and Ohio. The ethnic composition of these out of town locals was often different from the New York City locals and shops (photographs of the Southern locals, for example, show a large percentage of African-American members) and some of the out of town shoots include images of the communities in which the members lived.\
SUBSERIES I:D - MEETINGS AND EVENTS - 1938-1969.
District 65 own events and meetings at all levels are documented here--from meetings of individual small shops and locals (such as the Department Store Locals), to industrial and geographic divisions and sections (Apparel; Cosmetic and Drug; Button; Direct Mail; Dry Good; Food; Footwear; Hardware; Millinery; Metal; Textile; Toy and Gift; Downtown, Uptown, Midtown, and Eastside (Manhattan), and Brooklyn), to public meetings of the entire union and its parent bodies, and committees and subcommittees thereof, including the union’s various ethnic group affairs committees (Irish, Italian, Jewish, Negro, and “Spanish”—meaning Hispanic, mainly Puerto Rican), as well as meetings of the union’s retired members. Also included are regional and national meetings, conferences, and conventions, and events outside of the union in which District 65 participated or its members attended, such as state and national AFL-CIO conventions, and the Peekskill concert of 1949 and its violent aftermath. SUBSERIES I:E - MEMBERS AT HOME - 1946-1968.
From time to time the union’s members were interviewed and photographed where they lived, these images documenting in the process working people’s homes—interiors, furnishings, and fabrics--and working people at home, their dress and demeanor.
SUBSERIES I:F - MEMBERS AT WORK - 1938-1968.
Small group of images of District 65 members at their places of employment--mostly shown actually engaged in work--in venues including warehouses, factories, offices, department stores, and food service locations.
SUBSERIES I:G - POLITICAL ACTIVITIES - 1939-1969.
Throughout its existence, District 65 and its members were vigorously engaged in a broad range of political and social change activities, issues, and election campaigns, at the local, national, and international level, that were outside of the union’s own immediate bread and butter concerns. While these included other unions’ struggles, they also included its involvement in the civil rights movement (the union was an early supporter of the work of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.) and the “ban the [nuclear] bomb” and anti-Vietnam war movements. Also included are images demonstrating the union’s early support and lobbying for Medicare and Social Security, rent control, public transportation, Russian and Spanish war relief, the United Nations, establishing the State of Israel, supporting India’s independence from Britain, unemployment insurance, and local, state, and national progressive mainstream political candidates as well candidates for third parties such as the American Labor Party and Progressive Party, such as Progressive Party presidential candidate Henry Wallace. Moreover, when viewed chronologically, the images will frequently reflect the trajectory of the changing political landscape, and the union’s efforts to accommodate itself to that landscape, as for example initial opposition to United States involvement in World War II (union members carrying signs declaring, “The Yanks Are Not Coming”) and then post-Pearl Harbor huge union-sponsored war bond rallies.
SUBSERIES I:H - PUBLICITY - 1940-1967.
Documents the publicizing and promotion of services and events the union offered its members, such as its own medical plan, hiring hall, department store (“Consumer Service”), nightclub, drama club, and theater parties, directed to its members, as well as its efforts to promote itself and its activities to organizations and individuals outside of the union, through radio and television broadcasts, press conferences, and filming. In addition, the production and promotion of the union’s newspaper, and its staff are also documented.
SUBSERIES I:I - SOCIAL, CULTURAL, RECREATIONAL AND EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES - 1938-1969.
An organization that included large numbers of lively young people needed to--and did--offer its members numerous opportunities for socializing and recreation, a broad category that included parties (aka “socials”), dances, holiday celebrations (Christmas, Hanukkah, Easter, Halloween, St. Patrick’s Day, Purim), fiestas, picnics, boatrides, music, song, comedy, and theatrical performances (including well-known popular entertainers of the time like Harry Belafonte and Sam Levenson performing at the union’s own nightclub and supper club in the penthouse in its headquarters building), as well as sports such as baseball, softball, men’s and women’s basketball and bowling, boxing, and swimming. The union also documented the numerous contests it sponsored, including vacation-contest winners frolicking at Zunbarg’s resort in the Catskills, in the summer and in the snow, and beauty pageant contestants posing (igniting a pre-feminist-movement controversy in the pages of the union newspaper—both in its letters section and in the internal captions for the images that characterized them as “cheesecake”). Also included are images showing the myriad cultural activities the union offered to its members--both as consumers (through special performances for the union by a range of artists, such as the Katherine Dunham Dancers) and as creators--through the union’s own chorus, band, orchestra, and drama groups that presented pageants, sketches, skits, and full plays--including dramas (“Death of a Salesman”) and musicals and comic parodies written especially for the union (for example, “Thursdays ‘Til Nine” a musical about working in a department store, and “Plant in the Sun”—probably a parody of Lorraine Hansberry’s “Raisin in the Sun”). Also documented are union clubs featuring hobbies such as stamp collecting, chess, and bridge, classes in modern and ballroom dancing, and the numerous cultural and recreational activities and outings that the union offered its retired members (the latter perhaps extensively publicized simply because it demonstrated that its members were able retire in some comfort and security, because of benefits conferred by union membership). Cultural exchange also had a highly visible role in the union, with visits to the union by leaders of labor unions and labor parties from around the world, including Europe, Asia, Latin America, and African countries emerging or newly-emerged from colonialism (Kenya’s Tom M’boya was one) duly recorded, as well as visits by domestic groups such as college and high school students. Also photographed were educational and vocational training opportunities offered by the union to its members, including classes in foreign languages, labor history, and the arts, as well as courses to prepare members for white collar occupations, such as typing and stenography, and as well as for more industrial work, featuring training in using industrial machinery.
SUBSERIES I:J - WORLD WAR II - 1941-1956.
The union was deeply involved in the war effort, as well as the war’s aftermath, on both an individual and organizational level. This can be seen in through the numerous images of going-away and welcome-home celebrations, furloughs (and occasional funerals) for individual union members (mostly, but not all, male) as they entered and served in the military (captions usually include the branch of the military, members’ ranks, and occasionally indicate whether they had enlisted or been drafted). Also documented are home-front activities ranging from tin foil, war bonds, and blood drives to petitions and rallies urging the opening of a second front, to members serving in volunteer civilian defense-related capacities such as air wardens.
Series II, Interpositives, consists of 5,200 preservation copies created from the original negatives in Series I.
Series III, Duplicate Negatives, consists of 5,200 duplicate negatives produced for printing purposes from the 5,200 preservation copies in Series II.
Arrangement
Organized in three series: I: Negatives 1938 - 1968; II: Interpositives; III: Duplicate Negatives.
Historical/Biographical Note
District Council 65, United Automobile Workers (UAW) was organized in 1933 by a group of Jewish workers employed in dry goods warehouses on New York's Lower East Side. In 1935 it became a local of the Wholesale Dry Goods Employees Union; subsequently, it affiliated with the Distributive Trades Council of New York and the Retail Wholesale and Department Store Union (RWDSU); it joined with the UAW in 1979. The union went out of existence in 1994, when bankruptcy forced it to close.
Between 1937 and 1942, District 65 was at the center of a group of left-wing locals in New York City that organized large numbers of warehouse and retail workers; it later expanded its organizing to include white-collar workers in publishing and universities. Politically and socially active in areas beyond its own immediate concerns, District 65 was an early participant in the civil rights movement, as well as one of the first labor unions to publicly oppose the war in Vietnam. It took a progressive stance within its own organization also, with rank and file members playing an active role in their union.
Bibliography: District 65 Publications:
The Union Voice: August 1934 - April 23, 1935
The New Voices: April 23, 1935 - August 15 1937
New Voices: August 15, 1937 - January 7, 1945
Union Voice: January 7, 1945 - June 6, 1954
Publication of the RWDSU: June 6, 1954 - July 4, 1954 (two issues)
RWDSU Record: July 4, 1954 - January 8, 1961
The 65er: January 8, 1961 - July 1969
The Distributive Worker: July 1969 - 1994
American Federation of Labor. Wholesale Dry Good Employees Union. Local 19932 (New York, N.Y.).; Brown, Frank; Distributive Trade Council of New York .; Distributive, Processing, and Office Workers of America. District 65.; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America. District 65.; Livingston, David; Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union. Local 3 (New York, N.Y.).; Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union.; Robinson, Cleveland L. (Cleveland Lowellyn), 1914-1995; Wholesale Dry Goods Workers Union (New York, N.Y.).; Labor union meetings |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Labor unions |x Officials and employees |x Social life and customs.; Negatives (photographic); Strikes and lockouts |x Retail trade |z New York (State) |z New York.; Strikes and lockouts |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Work environment |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.
- Location Guide
  - Negative #s - 1-1098 (Box 1)
  - Negative #s - 1099-2140 (Box 2)
  - Negative #s - 2141-3233 (Box 3)
  - Negative #s - 3234-4715 (Box 4)
  - Negative #s - 4716-5847 (Box 5)
  - Negative #s - 5848-7177 (Box 6)
  - Negative #s - 7178-8409 (Box 7)
  - Negative #s - 8410-9697 (Box 8)
  - Negative #s - 9698-10908 (Box 9)
  - Negative #s - 10909-12218 (Box 10)
  - Negative #s - 12219-13423 (Box 11)
  - Negative #s - 13424-14609 (Box 12)
  - Negative #s - 14610-15982 (Box 13)
  - Negative #s - 15983-17276 (Box 14)
  - Negative #s - 17277-18764 (Box 15)
  - Negative #s - 18765-20294 (Box 16)
  - Negative #s - 20295-22413 (Box 17)
  - Negative #s - 22414-23966 (Box 18)
  - Negative #s - 24463-26393 (Box 19)
  - Negative #s - 26394-28016 (Box 20)
  - Negative #s - 28017-29157 (Box 21)
  - Negative #s - 29158-30170 (Box 22)
- Series I. Negatives, Bulk, 1940-1959; 1938-1969 (bulk 1940s-1950s)
  - Subseries I:A - Demonstrations, Rallies, Parades, Strikes - 1938-1969
    - A. Bier Wright Bigil Pickets, Sep 10, 1946 (Negative 2824)
    - A. Cohen Arbitration, in Negotiation and Shop Meeting; A. Cohen, Strike Fund; Strike Fund Thermometer, May 20, 1958; Jan 1959; undated (Negative 16575 - 16576; 17033 - 17041; 24280 - 24283; 19785)
    - A. Hirsch Demonstration, Jun 28, 1949 (Negative 5304 - 5306)
    - A. J. Siris Pickets, Sep 18, 1946 (Negative 2831 - 2834)
    - A. S. Beck Strike Publicity Committee; A. S. Beck, Miles and National Shoe Strike Meeting, Jan 10, 1952; Jan 1968 (Negative 8307 - 8308; 25376 - 25378)
    - Abraham and Strauss: Campaign in Hempstead, New York (Includes Exterior Shot of Store and Picket Line Shots); Shoe Market Picketing Abraham and Strauss, Hempstead; Leaflet Distribution, Mar, 1955; Mar 12, 1955; Apr 16, 1955; Jan 28, 1956 (Negative 13883 - 13891; 14603 - 14606; 14039 - 14047)
    - Adam Hat Leaflet Distribution, Dec 12, 1944 (Negative 2024 - 2026)
    - Admiration Picket Line, May 29, 1940 (Negative 387 - 388)
    - Advance Sample Strike Picket Line, 1968 (Negative 24214 - 24216)
    - Agee Quilting Lockout, Nov 3, 1952 (Negative 9881)